[Music]
the same as in 1 & 2 we need cart
跟第一部分和第二部分一样
this is photocopy cards 160 GSM scissors
我们需要卡纸 这里是160克的
need no explanation and glue the same
剪刀 不解释
same glue as was explained in part 1 so
胶水 不解释  胶水教程1详细说过了
there are five kinds of v-fold the first
这是五种类型的V形折
is the the right angle default this is
第一种是直角V形折 教程2第一部分解说过了
explained in part 1 the second is the
第二种 锐角V形折
acute angle v-fold these also explained
也是教程2第一部分解说的
in part 1 the third is the point of view
第三种 山形V形折
fault this is V Falls part two and the
在教程3 V形折第二部分溜过
two single V fold is also V Falls part
第四种 钝角V形折 也是教程3第二部分
two and the fifth and final type of V
第五种最后一种V形折
fold this is the asymmetric V fault
异形状V形折
this is too tall it's all about the
这节教程的主角
asymmetric v-fold most v-folds most pop
大多数V形折或者说
up mechanisms are centered on the on the
大多立起结构都是
spine fold and they're completely
垂直对齐主折线的
symmetric so the asymmetric V fold is
它们是完全对称的
useful it takes the takes the design off
非对称V形折在偏中心设计很好使
center and is why it just makes the
简直跟鲇鱼一样的存在
whole thing much more interesting those
能盘活整个设计
are it's very varied so I've got a whole
我这列举了
array of them here everyone different it
它们常见的几种形态 每个都不一样
all depends on the angles on the pop-up
所有都是依赖立起结构角度
and the angles on the page and in each
和基础页的角度
case all four angles are different
每个例子四个角都不同
scientists show enough an array of these
所以我就随意拎个出来举例子
[Applause]
they're very hard to actually work out
很难主观臆测会制作出
what the what shape you're going to make
什么形状
so you either need to know it's good to
所以不断试错
make just make trial and error make a
是掌握这种V折不错的方法
whole series alternatively I'll explain
或者我的书里有个章节解释了
in a minute in my book there's a
如何做选择
reference set that you can look at so so
有兴趣可以去了解
so here they are as you can see
就像现在看到的
they the angles just moved all over the place and
稍微改变角度 就产生不一样的形状
have an enormous amount of potential
具有很多种的可能性
right take a face sheet and fold it well
来吧 拿张卡纸做基础页
so here's a base sheet thoroughly
多折一折
creased as always counts can't stress
一直到折起后
that enough fold it back on itself and
不会有反弹
again and again so opens and closes nice
确认展开合上都是良好 顺滑
and smoothly we'll take a sheet of cards
再来拿出张卡纸
cut it in half fold it in half there
剪一半 对折
most nice pop-ups when you want the two
大多数立起结构
angles on each side in the pop-up piece
你都是想要两边角度对称的
to be symmetric so most pop-ups most
所以大多立起结构、
v-folds having folded it in half you
大多V形折一般先会对折
then fold the tabs on to it in this case
然后折起粘口
all four angles are different the two
现在的这种 四个角都是不一样的
angles on the pop-up and the two angles
即立起结构的两个角
on the base they're all different so in
和基础页上的两个角，他们都不同
this case having folded it in half just
在这里 折叠起来
cast a little wedge wedge acid the
沿着立起结构对折边
bottom corner this is your folded sides
在底角剪出一个楔形口
so we just just cut a wedge out and now
we now we fold the gluing tabs on to it
然后制作粘胶水的粘口
so start with one side fold it maybe you
从一边开始
make quite a quite a large angle and
先制作一个大角度的侧面
maybe trim those chill nose corners down
粘口边上修正一点
a bit more
so there we are and then the other one
这样差不多了
let's make it much more acute so we'll
另一个做个更偏锐角的
come right up like this so we've got the
马上开始
two angles on your pop-up piece are
这样现在的立起结构
completely different and again you know
有两个完全不同的角
just cut that into the gluing time now
修一下粘口
you put this on the put this on the page
修完后放基础页上
this is the very fold always falls in
V折折叠收起时
the direction that the V is pointing
一般是朝向V指的方向
it's going to be on your page something
在基础页上的体现是
like this
会超前倾倒
so it's going to fold down forward so
所以在粘贴时
you need to position it up near the top
应该是粘在基础页
of the page
偏后一点位置
lay up the central crease with the
粘口的折痕紧贴
gulley on the base so the central crease
基础页的中折线
of the pop-up is lined up with the the
立起结构和基础页的中折线平行相交
crease of the base now mark the small
现在在小角度边做个标记
angle so you on your pop-up you've got a
立起结构现在是有一个大角 一个小角
big angle and a small angle but this
我们标记的是小的
small angle so here's the line now this
来 跟我右手一起画条线
is a crucial bit you flip the whole
划重点 这里是关键
thing over so now you've got the big the
整个立起结构翻个面
big angle on the pop-up above the small
现在红色卡纸大角度会在
angle on the page so if you were to glue
基础页划线的小角度面上方
it down following that line you could
如果直接沿线上胶水
glue it down like this in which case the
效果就会成这样
whole pop-up would lie flat when the
立起结构会平摊在基础页上
when the page is flat but in this case
这不是我们想要的效果
you want it to be in dimension you want
这里我们想要立体的效果
it 3d so you move this move this piece
所以把角度略微向内收一收
in slightly and it's just got to be
也就是粘的时候
glued down somewhere between the line
粘口放在
you've marked and the central central
标记的线和中折线之间
gully of the the page and according to
另一边的粘口粘在哪
where you can learn it that would affect
会影响最终的形状
though the shape that you end up with so
结果说话
I'll just glue that
直接上胶水吧
the really crucial thing with this is to
再强调下最重要的：
make sure you flip it over so you get
翻转立起结构
the large the large angle on the pop-up
立起结构大角度边粘在
sticking over the small angle on the
基础页有小角度边的这面
page so here we are they make sure that
就像这样
you're gluing tab isn't going over there
要确保粘口不超过中折线谷沟
over the central gully if it does just
如果超过
trim it back a bit so that's that one
要剪掉那些超出部分
glued down now put the whole thing into
一边粘好后
its closed position
合起立起结构到折叠状态
but glue on the other tab smear it right
给另一边上胶水
up to the crease bit more glue and then
涂抹均匀
fold it shut
折叠起来
so here we have an asymmetric free fold
这就是非对称V形折了
[Music]
all four angles are different the two
这种结构四个角都是不同的
angles on the pop-up a difference and
立起结构两个角不同
the two angles on the on the base are
基础页的两个角也不同
different so now I'll just do a little
下面我画个图解释下
little diagram to explain how that how
其中原理
that works so if we take this is the
假设
this is the base sheet with the with the
这是基础页
crease down the middle and I'll just
中折线在中间
copy this one we've got the angle that
我仿照下这个形状
it's glued down to is here this is where
这个角是刚粘的位置
the one side is glued we'll call that
和中折线呈的角定为 A
angle a on the other side we've got a
much much wider angle we'll call that
另一边很大的这个角定为 B
angle B on the pop-up piece is the is
立起结构用虚线表示
the dotted line we've got a big angle so
画个大点的角度
that's here with the with the tab and
画粘口
we've got a small angle here with the
画小角度面
tab and this is the rest of the cards
画粘口 和卡纸其它部分
so we call these C this is angle C and
定大角度为 C
this is angle D right the crucial thing
另一个角度为 D
is the angles on each sides the angles
关键来了：
on the pop-up plus the base must be the
一边的立起结构角加基础面的角
same on the left and on the right so in
等于另一边立起结构角加基础面的角
this case a plus C must equal B plus D
在这里就是 A + C = B + D
and the other factor is the angles on
另一个条件
the pop-up must be bigger than the
立起结构的两个角加起来
angles on the on the base so C plus D
要大于基础页的两个角之和
must be bigger then a plus B I'll just
也就是 C + D > A + B
turn that around so you can so you can
我转下方向到镜头 看着更清晰
see it clearly so a and B are the angles
A和B是基础页上的角
on the base C and D are the angles on
C和D是立起结构上的角
the pop-up
so a plus C must equal B plus D so that
A + C = B + D
you have balance and so that the whole
这样达到了均衡
while thing stands up and doesn't lie flat on
为了让结构立起不趴在页面
the page the angles on the on the pop-up
立起结构的角之和
must be bigger than the angles on the
必须大于基础页上的角之和
page so C plus D must be bigger than a
也就是 C + D > B + D
plus B I've got a few books that
下面介绍几本书
demonstrate the asymmetric v-fold first
演示非对称V形折
dinah topia so here it is the pop-up
第一本《恐龙帝国》
that the dinosaur is rising from the
这个恐龙就是基于
dinosaur is rising from an asymmetric
非对称V形折
v-fold so you'll see that the angle here
可以看到立起结构的角
on the pop-up is bigger than the angle
大于基础页的角
on the page and the angle here on the
另一面这边立起结构的角
pop-up is smaller than the angle on the
小于基础页上的角
page so that's the first one the the
这就是第一个例子
angle on the pop-up the two angles on
立起结构上两个角度和
the pop-up are the same as the two
等于基础页的两个角之和
angles on the page so when the page is
页面完全展开时
flat the pop-up is flat the second book
立起结构也会摊平
is B where de storybook wolves
第二本《当心狼》
beware the storybook wolves and in this
one this is by a paper engineering by
作者是
Corrine Fletcher I think she's a really
赵四 [见视频末尾:)]
great paper engineer so here it is this
他是个了不起的纸艺工程师
fairy falling out of the page you can
这里是个小仙女落出页面
see the central the central gully on
可以看到中折线和仙女的谷沟
that on the ferry is really off-center
是偏离中心的
so this is an asymmetric v-fold you can
这是个非对称V形折
see it's asymmetric the central crease
可以观察到V形折的中折线
of the of the default is not lined up
没有跟主轴线
with the spine it's coming up with an
在一条线 而是有个角度
angle so this is the asymmetric V fold V
这就是非对称V形折
folds fold down in the direction the
立起结构V指向的方向
direction that the V is pointing so
就是立起结构合闭的方向
there is as you close the page the V
fold folds up into it normally pop-ups
are always built further up the page so
everything remains within there within
the frame of the book the way their head
is lifted up that's just a small
parallel fold built into the gulley
whether the v-fold attaches to the page
you can see that if I turn it round
slightly you can see that's a parallel
fold raising her head and the last one
I'd like to show you is the little fish
最后要介绍的是
who cried shark and this has got a
《哭鲨小鱼》
massive messy shark at the end these
最后页的鲨鱼
both the head and the tail they're both
头和尾部都是非对称V形折
asymmetric v-folds you can see the
可以看到
central crease on both these pop-ups
这些立起结构的折线
lean lean away from the central gully of
都是偏离书的谷沟
the of the book and the tail this is a
最尾部是个反折
this is a counter fold so and again it's
严格说
actually an asymmetric one so you can
也是个非对称V形折
see that's giving you an extra pair of
extra pair of planes so that's a
symmetric V folds and all of that is
explained in even more detail in in this
以上就是本节教程啦
如果想了解更多
可以考虑下我的书「pop-up design and paper mechanics」
前面说的内容
这本书中都有
[字幕：Cash Yang][公众号：2274]
[Applause]
[Music]